[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gavin Henry and
today my guests are Shannon salbert and
Parker sbert Shannon is an inspiring
polyglot programmer product manager and
contract or Enthusiast after stint
during Technical Training for the
government her entrepreneurial Spirit
Led her to co-found sain in 2008 where
she consulted for over a decade before
transitioning to the development of Oben
Pro Parker is a developer with a passion
for building things both virtual and
physical he is the creator of OB oburn
background job framework Chief Architect
at D Scout and partners with his wife
Shannon at sain building Obin web and
Oben Pro Shannon and Parker welcome to
software engineering radio is there
anything I missed in your bios that
you'd like to add no no nothing for me
those are pretty robust bios was a
fabulous introduction thank you did I
get the name of your company correct one
of the few people who has you did
excellent so the goals for the show
we're going to explore the terms
reliability consistency and
observability in relation to job
processing and understand how Oben with
with Elixir and postgress Andor sqlite
deliver those features so let's get
cracking we're going to do a brief
overiew to start with of what robust job
processing is and then in my usual
format we're going to do about 10
minutes on five different topics to
understand how you guys deliver this
with your product those topics are going
to be open reliability consistency
observability and databases which in
this case are postgress and SQL so let's
dig in what do we mean by robust job
processing the big one so robust really
means batteries included it means that
when you install Obin as a package it
should be featureful ready to go with a
minimal amount of extra configuration
and have tools that you normally would
have to add on like KRON or scheduled
jobs or lots of other little bits so
when we say robust job processing it's
really just about how featureful it is
okay thank you Shannon anything to add
to that no that was it I probably would
have added uniquness to it but I think
his explanation was Splendid
and a job what do we mean by a job is
that um a discret bit of work or you
know part of a bigger workflow or well a
job in Obin wraps up basically the qame
the worker argument States into a
serializable struct that's what I would
say a job is yeah the goal is always for
some side effect it's to have some bit
of work that has a side effect it's not
a pure functional kind of thing it's a
side effect like sending an email or
processing a video or generating an
export or something those when we say a
job it wraps up all the arguments and
data necessary to perform that piece of
work and this would typically be
something you don't want to sit and wait
for as a user of a of a product or maybe
open just used completely stand alone to
do something people definitely use it as
a standalone kind of tool but I think
more often it's part of something that's
a like an online system a web Phoenix
application or something that's serving
up traffic and then has to do other bits
of work in the background okay and we
use the term robust because we know it's
going to get it done is that right yeah
I'll subscribe to that we like the term
yeah so on once it's all in the system
we can chill out and relax we know that
is going to perform it or you know if we
set it up it'll let us know why it
hasn't correct monitoring or whatever
we've chosen to suit okay so that was a
good completely high level overview of
what bu job processing in I guess we
could we could go into the state machine
I suppose the job State machine for it
but that's I think we'll get there we'll
get there okay yeah I think we'll touch
on that in the next section and then
revisit in each of the other ones to
back up our selection of words here
reliability consistency cool so Obin
what is it who would like to go first I
always start with the word robust and
we've just defined robust so let's have
another
go it's a background job processor it's
something that manages jobs in a
persistent way I think there's one
critical word here though is that it's
specifically for Elixir that's right the
language Elixir let's get on to the
brief history of Obin first of all
because I live in Scotland there's a
beautiful place called Obin so is there
any relation to that there is I'd love
to tell you that our children were
conceived there or there was some
Fantastical story woven around it but
for us we love the town of Obin we love
the little B and you could say that
there is another Elixir that is exported
from Obin which is very inspirational he
finds very
inspirational well that's cool well I
guess right then there's not many yeah
it's a beautiful place it's a beautiful
word nice and short and just has some
some good Aesthetics to it some symmetry
to it great symmetry cool and um when
did you release it give us the history I
think we just hit the five year we hit
the five year
anniversary about a month ago so about
five years AG February yeah so five
years ago was when it was first released
have you got any major lessons learned
since that first release oh yes yes we
absolutely have some lessons learned
that's a difficult one to prune down I
think we have separate lessons I would
say my primary lesson we didn't know how
successful it was going to be from the
offset but wanted a way to be able to
focus on it and give it time and and not
have it feel like a chore or a burden so
we always wanted to add some
monetization around it so the lesson is
if you do plan on monetizing something
in an open core kind of model like we do
that you should be very selective about
the features that you put in because
what once you put something in there it
never comes out and of course you're
always going to have this revisionist
kind of plan of like well I shouldn't
have done that we should have done that
I think it's worked out but I think if
if I were to give advice to anybody else
who's starting something I would say
start with the The Bare Bones and go
from there and don't just keep plowing
features into something yeah so just to
recap Obin is an open source
project that is Prim well that is for
the Elixir language it's a robust job
process processing engine and more but
there is a commercial aspect to that
open source project as well could you
just tell us about that yeah we probably
shouldn't have backed into that so there
is the open Source version which is just
called Oben and then we have two
commercial offerings that are built on
top of that one is Oben web which is for
observing and interacting with the jobs
and other is open Pro and that expans on
obin's functionality and adds a lot of
more advanced or complex functionality
that that businesses need as they grow
and just to be clear open web is just
exposing what's already there you know
so stop you for orchestrating your own
Telemetry interface or you know job
processing interface right absolutely
not is there a typical use case or a
really one that stands out that you use
to show off open that you could tell us
about we don't when it comes to specific
use cases especially for people who
reach out to us and trust us a lot of
those use cases are
confidential so I would say ftech energy
a lot of use there the the Norwegian
Postal Service depends on Obin that's a
highlight it's a highlight that was a
great day I think a a really common use
case like the the hello world of Obin is
sending emails in the background because
it's something that you want to make
sure happens but it's also something
that can be kind of slow or you want to
schedule sometime in the future and I
think that's kind of the the entry the
Gateway into using Obin I agree okay can
you back up that example with some sort
of numerical data throughput size you
know how many things can sit in a queue
obviously that'll be dependent on the
receiving end of where you're sending
email and things but just to help the
listeners understand the scale of Obin
well we have cases of over 1 million
jobs a minute over 100 nodes
workflows over a thousand jobs people
processing a 100 million jobs a day so
it scales pretty far a lot of it comes
down to the real limiting factor as far
as performance tends to be what a job is
doing because the whole point is that
there's some sort of side effect and
you're going to have external resources
there whether that's a network or CPU or
something like that so usually the
response time and we just want to make
sure that it has a minimal impact on the
database and that we can people can
process things and Obin is not a
bottleneck or a source of contention for
their system do you have a problem since
the the start of open that you think
back well the next thing that comes
along I know I've already solved this
and it was really hard so I've got that
confidence was there a really hard nut
to crack on on the journey so far I
don't think we've actually cracked the
hardest problem that's what I was
thinking too take us through that
hardest problem yeah so the hardest
problem has been scaling in a sense
despite what I just said because it Obin
runs in somebody else's application and
that's a lot of different somebody
else's we don't have any control over
the hardware the number of nodes the
number of cues they run what their
database version is how they deploy how
they deploy yeah because you don't have
control over that you have to build
things out in sort of a lowest common
denominator way where you know there's
going to be reasonable performance in
any system so and that's something that
we just kind of learn little lessons on
and improve over time why does it run in
someone else's application just so the
list understand because the jobs are
somebody's own business logic that runs
in in their application because it's a
it's a package it's not a standalone
it's not like a SAS app where you send
something off and it runs like we're
running the jobs for you it's integrated
with a certain amount of autonomy yeah
okay I understand it's could be glass as
a plugin but it's there much more than a
plugin but and similar other Frameworks
whenever you have some type of a inous
job you want to do or that slow You'
reach for its robust job processing tool
set wouldn't you and that's what this is
for Elixir yeah it's an add-on package
it's lightweight some say plugin some
say
dependency Do you have a best fit for it
or is that not a thing I think it
broadly fits into any Elixir application
personally I mean I don't know that
there's a it's pretty broadly used and
some of the examples that Shen get
before about different Industries we
know of it like it's part of the boiler
plate that people use when they start a
new Elixir application all the way up to
some of the mega companies in The Elixir
space using it so I don't know if
there's a a best fit in scale or even
category industry yeah well I'll give
you two examples of where I use it
personally I've got an open source
project that uses it to deliver analytic
reports much like
plausible. I another open source project
use it and then in my day job we run
probably a couple hundred jobs a day
through it and what I how I architected
that is any external call to a a third
party API as a job and a worker so we
have a situation where we speak to an
API to build the customer's account you
know all the features around that the
different applications in that API that
need to be to receive a post basically
with a blobber Jason and every one of
those is a worker job and once it's
finished it pops another job in the
queue so it's all Daisy Chained and that
works really well you know when when
there's an outage on the API or there's
a a 500 you know it will bail out sit
there and I've had a que a job set for
maybe a week before anyone's noticed
that is not doing what it should be and
they just click retry and I personally
love it but anyway just wanted to add
the other use case that's brilliant
that's such a fabulous example of the
persistence yeah and just how you can
retry a job and it's got all the
metadata and everything I just love it
that's why I got you guys on right so I
think we've done a fairly good job of
discussing what open is so we'll drill
into the different terminology before we
move into the next sections so let's
Envision with the use case youve both
explained we've got a marketing campaign
for example we've got a million emails
to send out but somebody needs to sit in
front of the web browser and click to
schedule that job so take us through
that and and then what parts of once
that job's in the queue you know what's
been submitted with it for example what
gets looked up how does open get told
about the job how does it indicate that
it's worked if it doesn't work what does
it do from that point would that be a
good use to case to explore so we said
before that jobs are data so there are
different components to this which is
there's a worker which is a a module
Elixir module that has a defined
interface and then there are Q's which
are it's a name to group workers or jobs
and then there's the job job and the job
is a data so it's a bundle of the
arguments the worker the que and some
other metadata that you alluded to
before and the way that the state
Machine Works is you insert this into
the database um I don't know if we've
mentioned we've mentioned persistence
before but the persistence here is a
relational database so SQL typically
postgress and so we're you insert that
job into postgress and it has either a
scheduled state or an available State
and and Obin will then notify all of the
running instances all the running nodes
so nodes are earling parlance for
different instances it could be
different servers they don't have to be
because it just horizontally will just
transparently scale out but it notifies
the various cues if a node happens to be
running a queue that matches the job
that was just inserted it's notified
about it it will then go fetch that from
the database Market that it's executing
now do what ever work it has to do and
then based on whether that fails
succeeds is manually canceled something
like that it then writes it back into
the database with this final State and
there are some other nuances there like
if it failed then it will go back to a
retriable state will schedule it and
there's some back off and things that
happen there but that's roughly the
process that happens is that what you
meant by state machine that's exactly
what I meant aside from the acing in the
middle and perhaps the yeah the default
amount of retries but in his example I
think that's great yeah the state
machine is the status of the job yes it
work yeah and you can prioritize your
jobs as well that's probably something
that I mean there's a lot of little
intrinsic things you can do within that
but I would say priority is great right
oh as far as the extra metadata right
for your metad data that he was
mentioning how does the database tell
the other workers that there's something
ready to do is that something they
always look for and pull postgress or
how does that bit work this has evolved
over time initially we had a a trigger
function in postgress that would then
send a message using postgress pubsub
we're going to say pubsub a lot as we
keep talking I think it's really Central
to the way that Obin does stuff it could
be a drinking game yes pum sub PB sub
drinking game I think it could it would
push a notification out and then that's
what would be picked up by all the nodes
it be broadcast to the nodes and if it
matches a Q then the Q knows to fetch
that doesn't work for schedule jobs
though because you could insert
something now but it's scheduled to run
a minute from now or an hour from now
and so you can't broadcast something so
then Q's would pull every one second to
go look for jobs well we mentioned
before that there are some companies
that run hundreds of cues or they run
hundreds of nodes and you can't have all
of those polling that's just way too
much load on the database especially for
most of the time there's nothing there
most cues aren't saturated all the time
so it evolved into where every node has
a central process which we call a Stager
and the Stager there's a elected leader
among the whole cluster so only one
Stager runs and then the Stager polls
and it checks for available cues and
then it broadcasts to the relevant cues
you have available jobs and then only
those go and run and by doing this we
reduced the number of connction like
queries every minute by a factor of well
60 times whatever however many um nodes
you have so it was very significant so
Parker could you just take us through
what Stager is again Stager is our term
for it's a gen server which is a orlay
and elixir concept of a standalone
process that can send messages to itself
receive messages manage some bit of
state and operate autonomously and so in
the context of Obin the Stager is a
single process across the whole cluster
and it uses a leadership mechanism to
figure out which one is the should be
the the leader Stager and it's the thing
that pulls the database every second to
look for scheduled jobs and available
jobs and then it notifies cues all
across the cluster that they have jobs
to run and by using this you alleviate
having every queue on every node have to
pull which dramatically reduces the
number of transactions and queries every
minute understand yeah just to close off
this section before we move on to
reliability you mentioned that you can
have scheduled jobs in the future and
that's something I do as well where we
have somebody initiates a job to go and
build something against a third party
API so it starts the first worker
completes inserts the next one Etc so
there's a sort of cascade daisy chain
but we also have something that runs
every 3 hours to go and pull another API
to check for status updates on support
tickets you know and update the database
so I just thought it be a good example
to explain for the listeners okay so I
think we've done a good sort of midlevel
overview of all the bits we'll discuss
more of those in the next sections but
now I'd like to talk about liability
you've spoken about the Stager process
or node would we like to take a second
just to Define reliability in relation
to Obin what is reliability so in terms
of reliability I think that with Obin
using at least one semantics that means
that a job is guaranteed to run at least
once and if it runs and it fails there's
a safeguard there to bring the job back
and make it run again much like you
stated in your example of how you use
open
part of the way openin is built that's
different from other systems or at least
previous systems because I know some job
processors in other languages have
picked this up now is that jobs aren't
deleted from the queue the moment that
they run they stay in the queue and
their state is transitioned so you can
go look at it which I think we'll talk
about later but because of that you're
guaranteed that if something Happ like
if you're the somebody trips over the
power if the node goes down or something
that the jobs not lost so you have this
guarantee that within the transactional
database you're not going to lose your
work which particular bits of Obin
Elixir do you use for this type of
feature all of
them all of them the supervision trees
registry heavily process monitors
Dynamic supervisors process
groups yeah it's I think pretty much the
whole standard Library is in there and
then some things that aren't even that
are deeper you know erlang OTP concepts
are in there too it all comes to play
it's just the way that you build a
system that can save itself rescue
itself monitor itself it's the way that
you build stuff in earling in OTP so
when you state that it will definitely
run once the whole of the beam and
elixir language has a massive part in
that I think so I think you can't
downplay the role of postgress in the
whole thing that's that's really
important as well but the beam has the
fact that you don't have threads in
separate processes like if you want to
scale up if you K can't manage to
process things you're not going to have
a thread crash or a process crash and
then drop all those jobs because in in
the beam you have different separate
processes and all of those processes are
supervised and so you know when they go
down and the supervisors are then
supervised and so you know this Q is
having a problem shut down that Q it's
got State start it back up all those
things just make sure that it keeps
running smoothly without taking down
whole wings of your application so I'll
keep going back to this email example so
we've got a million emails scheduled to
run would we would the design part in
there be there's a job for email to send
or is there a a database table with a th
emails in there or a CSV file to to Loop
through and then send how deep do you
break apart that email job so say for
example there was a power outage or
something you don't want to send the
first half a million emails again people
do this in different ways depending on
how many things you really want to
insert it could be that you bundle a
bunch of emails say you you chunk it and
so that every email has 10 or 100 or or
something like that and then you're
guaranteed that once that batch of 10
runs that they're not going to resend
but there's always the downside that if
you don't do them all individually you
could get to the 10th one and have the
previous nine double send so the way
most people do this is a single job per
email it's not always convenient to put
a million emails in but it is the most
reliable way to do it and there's no
problem with that type of use case
because you've already explained that
okay which part of a platform or system
are not reliable that open helps solve I
don't want to cast dispersions on anyone
but I would say the application around
Obin is probably the most unreliable
part that's not reliable that's true
that tends to be one of the biggest
problems is that it's sharing it's
sharing the Ecto pool with the host yeah
it's sharing the Ecto pool and it's
sharing the
database and if the Ecto pool is starved
because other parts of the system are
are running then it's going to look like
Obin can't fetch jobs or it can't act
jobs or the things that it needs to do
to run when really it's kind of a shared
resource problem Ecto is that um You
probably call it an OM when you OB
object relationship yeah yeah it's the
database adapter thing in Elixir yeah
and the out the box it has for one of a
better term of thread pool you know 10
connections or something that you need
to make sure you you manage if open are
going to take a few of those yeah and so
Obin shares those each Oben instance
hold Ian it depends on what you use for
pubsub but it might hold one extra
connection to the database for each node
but you don't have to use that but it
will always have to use the Ecto pool or
an Ecto pool of some kind just to have
those connections to do queries and do
the things it needs to do and say for
example the application is Rock Solid
you know the application developer is
very proud of what they've built and
it's nothing to do with them but they've
not spent a lot of time on the progress
side and that goes down if you restor
from backup the jobs are in the the
worker tables they'll just get picked up
again and looked at that' be right
that's right so it's just your standard
database management type thing op which
is also another benefit is one of the
the many benefits of using postgress as
your Q instead of something else that
maybe doesn't have backups like if
you're using rabbit mq or redus or
something where you don't have the same
Cadence of backups or a follow
or something like that so that you
guarantee that you don't lose data if
something crashes or the hard drive goes
or whatever it is and the architecture
that you use for the database is
completely up to you you could have a a
right only cluster where the jobs get
inserted in a a readon cluster where
they get pulled that type of
thing no it whatever it has to have read
write access because polling a job is
still an update action because you're
transitioning the state so it will write
something what was the other oh yeah
because it's treating the whole thing as
a state machine you need to acknowledge
the fact that you've queried it and that
increments something like this job has
been retried eight times out of a Max of
20 whatever you set on the the queue mhm
excellent I think I'm a bit weird and
and love talking about retry
algorithms I did once tried to get
someone else on the show who invented
the ethernet try algorithm but um it
didn't work out so if you could tell me
what you reached for for yours that' be
great so is that neel's algorithm is
that the no ethernet's not the same as
TCP right the ethernet's the whole frame
I think of the packet TCP is a bit of it
anyway yeah so if a job fails what have
you used to look at that and back it off
and all those types of things for us
it's the exponential back off with
Jitter so do we have different
algorithms in different spots yeah I
think that's the one that for
reliability especially we depend on so
there's some element of
randomization so if there are 10 jobs
and there's contention on that resource
and they're rescheduled at the same time
then you're going to have that same
contention so using that algorithm with
Jitter inserts that random number within
the calculated future attempts and
breaks that up yeah I've seen that
myself with we had a the scenario
explained where we speak to a third
party API to build various bits of a
whole customer account it was down or
there was some issue and I clicked the
nice select all job tick box and just
clicked retry them all and I we found
some race conditions in the API
basically that we were speaking to it
was provisioning things that didn't lock
you know so it looked as if there was 10
things available and then 20 jobs came
and then when they all tried to take
that resource and use it just didn't
work so it's good to use open to stress
test third part
apis it's very quick and it's very good
the biggest place that back offs really
apparent is with job Rees but is used in
lots of other places internally as well
because database queries fail like
there's either pool contention or things
are just slow or who knows what's
happening so we have little retries
around a lot of other parts but
something important to note for jobs in
particular is that you can customize the
back off too so sometimes people use a
fixed back off it's like it's just it
tries again 10 seconds later or they
have their own other algorithms so
that's kind of a pluggable thing that
people can do that's good to know okay
I'm going to move us on to my next
section called consistency someone like
to have a go of defining consistency
consistency yeah this I think is
actually a little bit harder than the
other one I tend to use persistence in
my definition of consistency which is
probably not ideal well for the
listeners how I develop this show is I
took your strap line and then broke it
up so this is one of the the key terms
in your strap line yes yes I'm well
aware that it is our verbi asion our
fault the goal just to make us really
regret those particular word choices
which we kicked around for quite a while
yeah so there are I guess we could point
out a few things the fact that jobs are
only going to run on a single node just
the tooling that's used the queries that
are used mean that there's no chance
you're going to have something run
double and not record that it has two
attempts so if you say the max attempts
are two you're not going to have it run
three times you're not going to have the
same job run on two different nodes at
the same time these things are
prohibited by the queries that we use
and the way that things are structured
and then another big one is around
leadership and so Obin is a hybrid
distributed and centralized application
so because we're relying on a database
there's this element of centralization
but because you have multiple nodes and
they're all acting autonomously there is
a distributed system that's behind it
that means to make sure that things are
say cron jobs are only inserted once or
there's only one node that's going to
clean up old jobs or things like that we
have a single leader and the elected
leader is the one that does it we don't
have to use a distributed consensus
algorithm like raft or something to do
it because we have centralized
leadership and if that leader goes down
that's taken care of by The Elixir tools
and what the beam can do yeah and the
leaders always go down because people
deploy new applications and so if you're
doing a blue green kind of thing your
old leader is going to shut down and the
new one's going to take it going to come
up yeah that's what we do when we deploy
incremental changes on this application
I explained there's two nodes they will
Canary deploy so one will good down and
upgrade if it upgrade doesn't work it'll
try again Etc but just to back up your
consistency explanation there there in
this application that I was doing you'd
be sat in front of it and you'd be
uploading a PDF so that PDF needed to
get onto support ticket so initially it
took quite a while for that PDF to
upload cuz it was big so thought oh this
is perfect for Obin I'll just have it as
a job gets inserted into the queue the
PDF is saved on the file system of the
container so will go and fetch it but
then it wasn't consistent because
depending on what node you hit when you
were uploading the PDF it would only be
on the file system of that Docker
container so if it so happened that the
node that ran the job to grab the PDF
and upload it hit the right container to
look at the temporary storage it would
work but then 2 seconds later another
job would come along because it couldn't
find it because it was connecting to a
different node so I had to completely
change it to have shared storage so that
use case of an asynchronous job to keep
consistent failed because the file
wasn't in a consistent place for Obin to
find it to upload it to the ticket
system so yeah you you kind of reach
with these great tools and then you
think oh it's I've just messed up
because I'm not designed it right you
know yeah that's one of the downsides of
always being in a distributed setup I
mean it scales horizontally in a
completely transparent way no matter how
many nodes you throw at it but that also
means that it's going to change some of
your design decisions about where you
store these resources yeah it took me a
while to actually realize that the
workers were individual on my setup
anyway and it was trying to find this
holder that didn't exist in one place
but it did in the other so didn't take
long to sort it but it is a different
way to design things for sure so how
does Obin provide this consistency with
regards to the new leaders if like you
say when you're doing new deployments
things get stopped and started so we
have kind of two pluggable mechanisms
one uses distributed orlay as a cluster
which is not a very popular mechanism to
do it now a shocking number of Elixir
applications don't use a cluster they
centralize through redus or postgress or
something like that yeah something so I
think when we pulled it was at least 40%
of even the people that we know that use
Obin they don't have a cluster so that
means that their individual nodes can't
talk directly to each other they have to
go through something that's kind of
centralized so we use use a centralized
leader as I mentioned before which means
that there's a table and whatever the
leader happens to be every node sort of
races to take ownership of a row in that
table and eventually that row expires
and when it expires another node can
insert its own and then it becomes the
leader so all the other nodes can see
whether they are the leader who is the
leader and it's a pretty simple
mechanism but it's guaranteed to be
consistent because there's just one
Central resource so that's kind of like
mutex shared mutex on a thread wouldn't
it be if the leader if the leader grabs
a row and manages to write and say
that's mine then everyone else comes
along and sees that there isn't one
available yep that's cool I'm one of
those 40% I run the nodes in the
cluster and that works really well cuz
some of the Telemetry interfaces you
know the Phoenix dashboard that shows
you everything that's going on that
works nicely with a cluster and you can
do a drop down and see what every no is
doing so it's worth the extra effort I
would say I think that it's recommended
I've heard Parker recommend it therefore
I recommend it so especially for people
that use web open web there's a package
behind it which is called open met for
metrics and there are lots of there are
different queries that happen like say
counting jobs across cues and things
like that that are pretty slow and we
don't want every node that you have to
do it we want one node to do it but you
want that data to be available on any
node so sort of like the situation you
mentioned with the file upload you don't
want to randomly like every time you
connect you're going to get a different
web node and the one that's the leader
would have the counts but the other one
wouldn't since we don't want that they
have to broadcast information between
each node so they all have a kind of a
consistent view of the stats and all the
metrics that we display but you don't
want to duplicate the work behind
getting that and just to close off this
consistency section so we've got the
example you said where they tried to
insert a record in the database and to
let everyone else know that that leader
has is in charge and then it's
guaranteed for a job to at least run
once and then it will be Reed so you
know that it's going to be consistent is
that correct I understand that right yes
there's also partially just the way that
you query postgress and the way that we
move things between states that adds a
little bit extra and then acing and
retry those are all parts of just
maintaining a consistent view of the
data as well is that more than like your
standard transaction type thing or it is
a little bit more than the standard
transaction there's something that is
part of a select query in postgress this
is very widely used for any system that
does postgress as a queue and it's
called skip locked and it's a way to
have different processes or different
connections query for the same data and
fetch things that are not actively being
fetched by another connection without
taking a lock on the entire table is
that something particular that postc
does or yes yes perfect okay so let's
move on to observability who would like
to go at to finding that so let's see
observability well you can see which
jobs are running in which cues that's
highly observable the fact that jobs
aren't pruned they stick around after
they've been ran and you can use that to
query and find out what's occurring in
that it's extremely observable yeah and
that's the database side that's yeah
pretty much what we mean by observable
yeah and that's because you took the
conscious decision of keeping the
records around and post grass and having
as much data as possible in that job
table yeah that kind of came from the
inspiration there is streams originally
like Kafka style streams but then more
through the lens of the way that reddis
Ed streams
where you have a stream of events and
different consumers can pull them and
process them and then acknowledge them
but they're not deleted or I guess it's
called compacted they're not compacted
right away so you can see information
about what happened after it happened
and that's where the idea came from for
that part of observability and is there
anything you utilize for observability
from Alexa and the beam in general we
use and practically abuse telemetry I
think that's fair to say so that's the
Telemetry package that's a standard
package that a lot of different
libraries use it was new newish at the
time Obin was created and wasn't as
widely used but we use it to instrument
everything so inspect yeah and why do we
need this observability in general I
guess so that you can diagnose what's
going wrong or what's going right in
your system you might need to do some
business Pres presentations on how many
jobs you're running and all that type of
stuff so Shannon said we practically
abuse Telemetry and that's kind of a
reference to things that we've built on
top of telemetry in open Pro so there
are features there like batch processing
or what we call relay which is like
distributed tasks those things use
Telemetry to transparently hook onto
what open's already doing and build on
it without modifying any part of the
open- source package
okay so that's like Beyond just
instrumentation or debugging level of
observability but actually hooking in
and building something else onto it
right in Telemetry if I recall in Elixir
you can sort of subscribe to those
events as well you know what's going on
that way okay I think we've done a good
job of pulling apart your strap line
seeing how it all works together yeah we
deserved
it so for the last part of the show I'd
like to explore what postest brings and
you mention obam can work with sqlite
explore some of the trade-offs between
selecting two or you know if they work
together nicely so first of all why did
you pick post SQL well it's one of the
most widely used databases in the world
I think everybody should as far as just
default SQL database choices it's I
think a go-to for many applications and
especially in the Elixir Community
there's major hesitancy around using
additional tools for distributed things
or caching so things like redis is it's
used but it's not a popular choice but
almost any application is going to have
a database and postgress is by far the
favorite tool for Elixir applications
much more than my SQL or I guess that's
about the only other practical option
much more than that so that's kind of
the why postgress part of it and it does
have other great properties that make it
easy to build something that has
batteries included out of the box like
it does have that skip locked and it
does have the pub sub stuff built in and
it does have great Json support so
there's a lot of good bits to it that
make it appealing choice and can you
just take us through again how you use
it with open just a refresher so for
example the job gets inserted the
leaders check that row ETA yeah so aside
from leadership which we talked about
before for coordination there's also
there's a table that holds all the jobs
every Row in that table which is called
the open jobs table is a job and that
has a state on it that we track and
attempt numbers and other metadata about
when things were inserted or not
inserted and q's which we have sort of
an overloaded notion of a q a q is both
the name of something to group jobs and
the name of a process that autonomously
fetches those jobs but cues then fetch
rows from that that match the name of it
its CU so like there's a default que by
default but a lot of people would have
say exports or something else and so it
runs queries on the jobs table to pull
these rows out do some processing on
them and then check them back in with
some other state and if I recall
correctly a job can have arguments as
well so variable pieces of data you can
give it so yeah yeah jobs Ally have ARS
there's another free form field called
meta that we use internally to add other
attributes like to indicate that
something is from a cron entry or
indicate something was snoozed multiple
times which is sort of like scheduling
it to process a few seconds later
there's a lot of other Rich data that
gets written for each job row yeah I use
the job ARS as basically it's possible I
think we insert a job with a customer ID
which is an ID on the post Crush table
so then the job is self-contained and
can just go and fetch the customer
details and you know to keep the logs
light and all the visible things and the
Privacy things it's just a a uid as an
ID so you can't really see anything in
the logs if ever got out you can put
anything you want in there can't you you
could but I mean aside from the fact
that it just going to take up space on
disk that probably redundant there's
sort of a freshness aspect to it so if
you put an ID in like you do and
something changes by the time that job
runs like maybe it's got some retries to
it and you fixed something in the row or
whatever the reference data was and that
fixes a bug then if you had put the
entire data structure in there that job
would never succeed whereas maybe
because you fixed it after it's retried
five or six times now the data is
updated when it fetches the fixed data
it will run which is to say just try to
keep job keep the args as minimal as
possible yeah that's what I do it's so
one simple ID the job itself is defined
as it calls other functions within
Elixir so if I've made a mistake and my
code is broken I haven't put all that
logic in the Standalone job that I've
defined the worker sorry so if it does
break and there's an error there I can
go back and fix the code do a hot reload
or a restart and the job just works so
You' got to Bear those things in mind I
think when you're designing your workers
try and keep them as generic as possible
well in my use case anyway so I I do
recall that you can use SQL light for
this what the tradeoff and the different
use cases for choosing one or the other
or both well you need something for
persistence and it's natural for small
isolated environments it's good for
engine abstraction having another engine
is great having one that isn't postgress
and it keeps us honest there is a term
that Parker uses here that I refrain
from using I will let him say it I don't
know why I dis like saying it you're
going to say the monkey term oh the
monkey patching thing yeah so I feel it
keeps us honest he refers to Monkey
patching when we discuss it so when we
say it keeps us honest so we have the
postgress engine and then pro has its
own separate engine which we call the
smart engine which has more advanced
functionality like Global concurrency
across all nodes rate limiting it's a
clean way to do that automatic batching
things like that and because we have
some abstraction around what that is
what that engine is we wanted to have at
least two in Obin itself so that we
could run tests on both and a lot of
people asked for SQL light for embedded
systems small environments like people
running nerves well yeah tiny little
devices and by having two of them we
know that all those abstractions work
cleanly and we don't have to maintain
some separate test suite and a separate
package but it also sort of proves out
that we're not relying on queries or
things that only work in postgress so
that if somebody did want to build it
for my SQL or some other type of
database that it would work yeah that's
a good way to keep the exra abstractions
there to make sure you're not just tied
into one database are there minimum
versions you have to run open with for
post grass I think we're at 12 are we on
12 yeah it's on 12 that's somewhat of
recent the we documented that 12 was
required over a year ago but we actually
used a feature from 12 within the past
couple of weeks for a consistency fix so
now it's 12 but 12 is over five years
old so it doesn't feel too aggressive it
did feel like a big jump I think we
supported back to 10 until a few weeks
ago yes yeah I think the Json support
has been there maybe since Version 9 or
something which is ancient but yeah
we're on 16 now aren't we I think yeah
the original version we supported was
9.6 because that's what added skip
locked we don't support mature versions
of erling or Elixir either so we're not
picking on anyone nice did you get just
touching the back a bit on the history
is there something was there a situation
along the timeline where you maybe
thought postr wasn't the right thing to
use or you saw something else you had to
rethink that selection or was it a
beautiful happy path the whole way we
have wish list yeah with postgress for
sure handling bloat yeah a much better
way to manage bloat in postgress would
be great that's the biggest thing on the
wish list I think so so we when we say
blow we mean dead rows rows that aren't
actively used but that the database
hasn't managed to clean up yet which is
just an artifact of the way that postes
concurrency controls are done an update
to any particular field just marks that
row and as an old row and creates a
duplicate most of the time this isn't a
problem but I wish it was better but
considering what it would take to do an
equivalent set of features and I
actually I can't I don't even know
another language that would let us build
things like workflows and chains and
batches and all the other stuff in Pro
or Global rate limiting in some other
technology so while we might have a wish
list it's like still very pleased
doesn't the way postrest do things it
has that background job that vacuum
things when the Roser it does yeah
compacts them but you have to repport
fresh data to not use the storage side
right yeah so two things that are very
relevant here in Pro 1.3 which is like
month or two old now we added
partitioning and so partitioning is a
feature of postgress that lets you have
like inheritance in tables and you can
split it based on some term so for
example splitting by job state which can
help with query performance because if
you're running a lot of jobs and you've
got millions and millions of jobs in say
a completed State you can query a
relatively empty available table and
that's just much faster but the other
really great benefit there is that it's
almost instantaneous to delete the table
so the autovacuum doesn't have to do as
much work and when you want to go
through and delete all the jobs from say
last week it just drops the table
instantaneously and and there's no
actual CPU load or and the bloat just
kind of goes away which is pretty
fantastic I think we should probably
touch on the nice way you've designed
this Open sauce product like everything
I use is in the the free version but if
we've got bigger or more complex as
users we have the ability to you know
contact you for support and then look at
what Pro brings and I think all we need
to do is change how we pull in the
package you know there nothing more than
that and some configuration so it's a
good way if we put our sustainability
hat on of how open source projects can
be sustainable so it's a good model not
to make it into too much of a pitch but
no thanks we that's wonderful so I think
we've got a bit of time to cover some
other shows people might like to listen
to and support of this I did one on
software Telemetry episode 4555 with
Jamie rale we did one on data
observability with Kevin who if I said
that correctly episode 507 and we had
the big guns on we had Jose valim on
episode 588 that was a real nice show
speaking to him about that all things to
do with Elixir so if you want to get up
to speed have a good with that we did
episode 5'11 With ant Wilson on supper
base so postgress is a service and a
really really enjoyable one on postest
performance if you guys haven't heard it
episode 583 with Lucas F I think it is
and then another one on job processing
is Maxim faiv on durable execution with
temporal so that was jobs that might
last two years you know and it was quite
an immense show that's another good one
to listen to Okay so we've got a bit
time for two quick questions before we
start wrapping up could you provide some
tips for any ongoing projects on where
to fit openen in so they they've reached
a point or you know there's something
that just screams why haven't you got
open in there this is something that I
see most of the people that come and
talk to us in are very active slack
Channel or on the Elixir Forum they're
already using Oben so I think the
primary place that we encounter people
who aren't using it yet are just within
the Forum yeah we'll see people even
people in The Forum are like I don't
actively use it but you might want to
look at this for this thing that you're
doing and I think it's just people who
aren't familiar with the Paradigm of
background job processors they're kind
of newer to programming or newer to we
development or they just haven't had to
manage things at a scale where it's not
okay to block and have somebody wait on
something to come in so I think there's
just a natural jump from you're learning
Elixir you're learning about the things
that it provides like tasks and then now
you've got a task that does something
async and it lasts five minutes well how
do you make sure that when your system
restarts in the middle of that F minute
processing that you're not just going to
lose what ever you were doing that's
where the persistent Q kind of comes in
and I think it's more of a matter of
educating about persistent cues in
general and how beneficial that is and
then hopefully that naturally leads to
Obin as a good choice in the Elixir
ecosystem yeah it certainly changed my
life with production software I only
recently came across this type of model
cuz I didn't really have anything that
needed it but when you have your own
experience sat in front of a browser and
you're like this doesn't this feels too
long you know and then you go oh this is
a whole way to do things and it
completely blows your mind of how you
should be doing stuff but me that's a a
weakness on my part but no and that's
exactly the kind of quote we'd like to
hear which is it changed my life
fantastic yeah I'm just like put it as a
job and a worker and forget about it you
know it's done it's great it takes a
little bit longer you know when you
break up all the different steps but it
fits nicely once you get your head
around it my last question what's the
most common issue you see when users are
trying to I'm going to say a adopt Obin
but maybe just use Obin or a job
processing framework what did they not
get that takes them a we well I would
think the naming of the cu's the typo
and the Q name and naming the cues it's
almost funny I think it's no I don't
mean that to make slide of somebody but
that comes up so often I would say
checking what version of Obin you're
using and whether or not you've named
your cues or if there's a typo in the Q
name is first and and foremost the
biggest support issues we encountered
yeah I think we had done like a napkin
calculation and I think 80% of the
issues people initially came to us with
were why aren't my jobs running it's
well you put it in a que that had some
it was like your own special Q name but
you never started a queue with that name
so there's nothing to run there's
nothing to run yeah yeah because the que
is run by a process isn't it to check
the database and all that type of stuff
yeah and part of the reason there is
that you want a certain amount of
concurrency for different types of work
so you could put everything into a
single cue and say you're only allowed
to do 10 concurrent jobs but then you'll
end up with things that process really
quickly and some others that are really
slow so if you're say you're processing
uploaded images that might be kind of
slow and then that's going to block
things that you want to be very quick
like sending a push notification so you
naturally end up modeling it where you
have different types of work in
different types of cues and they have
their own concurrency and getting into
that mindset I think there's a stumbling
point between oh I want to put this in a
different que and oh I need to actually
start that as its own separate queue
yeah that's something I need to look at
because I don't have any named cues
apart from out the box I think there's a
10 workers or something they're all
default yeah yeah the default is default
yeah so my scenario there would be I
can't imagine 10 people sat in front of
this application clicking create you
know but then just as you're speaking
there I'm thinking well I'm cascading
these jobs data chaining them and if
they run really quickly they might be
trying to sear jobs into the next queue
and that fills up that small list so I
haven't had any emails from App signal
tell me you know because they've got a
really nice out of the box open
monitoring QE system I don't know if
you've seen that we have that was a fun
surprise cuz they didn't reach out or
anything they just kind of built it yeah
it's really nice you just get alerts on
the job you can see the arguments and so
I've not had any triggers and I've not
had any complaints so I presume it's all
right I would just like to mention
anybody who is having an issue where
their jobs aren't running we appreciate
when you reach out we look forward to
building that trust within the community
if you have an issue we are available
we're here much appreciated okay so
let's wrap up it's time for my usual
question that I like to ask yes if there
was one thing that you'd like a software
engineer to remember from this show
shanon what would you like that to be
and then onto you Parker after well an
updated version of Obin I mean it
provides improved functionality so I
would ask that you keep your version of
Obin current okay nice one Parker
Shannon kind of covered both of them
stay up to date it doesn't languish we
release updates and fixes all the time
try to keep the issue tracker really
clean so if you have any problems let us
know we're eager to fix things and make
sure it's just a good clean
simple experience for everybody who
wants to come use it yeah you've been
very responsive whenever I've opened an
issue which I think was maybe once and
then I just do the simple depender bot
through GitHub that looks at my Elixir
list of dependencies and recommitted too
yeah I'll get a poll request on a Monday
morning to update open and it shows the
change log and I just click merge and
off we go redeploy is there anything we
missed that's key to this whole
discussion and that we've made
assumptions on that you can think of or
are we good I know you've done episodes
on Elixir before and I would imagine a
lot of your listenership is familiar
with Elixir and and what it is but I
have to say that the whole project would
be maybe not impossible but extremely
difficult with any other runtime so I'd
encourage people who are kind of curious
about what the language brings and what
the runtime offers to really check it
out it unlocks things that are immensely
difficult to do if not impossible in
other situations and people can follow
your company sa on Twitter but what
other ways can they get in touch you can
follow us on Twitter we're not
especially active it's mostly just kind
of announcements about things primarily
slack and the Forum are the best ways to
get in touch and that's your own Oben
slack no it's the Elixir Community slack
which is a pretty bustling thriving
slack but there's an Obin channel in
there okay yes um there's loads of good
things in that on that as well okay
Parker and Shannon thank you for coming
on the show it's been a real pleasure
this is Gavin Henry for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio and educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at SE-R doet
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at seo. slack.com you
can also email us at team sc-
radio.net this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening